CURRICULUM VITAE

IVO STEIMANIS

Frankfurter Str. 66, 35037 Marburg, Germany

☑ i.steimanis@gmail.com

L +49 174 9686328

Ivo Steimanis is currently doing his PhD within the *Shadow of the future* research project of Prof. Björn Vollan funded by the Bosch Foundation. In his research he investigates the impact of climate change on human behavior; such as pro-social behaviors, migration and other forms of adaptation. Therefore, he conducted research with people living in three of the most exposed regions to the impacts of rising sea-levels that could lead to displacement: atoll islands in Solomon Islands and coastal regions in Bangladesh and Vietnam.

RESEARCH INTERESTS

Environmental, Experimental & Behavioral Economics with a focus in Developing Countries. Thematic Focus: climate change migration nexus, local level governance in SSA

EDUCATION

1/2016 - present

PhD Candidate in Economics
Philipps-Universität Marburg, Germany
First Supervisor: JProf. Dr. Björn Vollan
Second Supervisor: Prof. Dr. Tim Friehe

Cumulative dissertation with four essays investigating the climate change migration nexus. The first essay lays the conceptual framework for studying the nexus; the second one investigates the (theoretical and simulated) impact of sea-level rise on discounting, migration and resource use; the third and fourth essay are based on lab-in-the-field experiments, where the former studies how pro-social behaviors are affected by rising sealevels and the latter investigates how trust is affected by the multiple expected interactions. The fieldwork for this dissertation included an extended stay in Solomon islands, as well as designing and planning of the research in Bangladesh and Vietnam.

10/2012 - 7/2015

Master of Science in Applied Economics, cum laude University of Innsbruck, Austria Supervisor: Dr. Björn Vollan

2-year masters program; personal thematic emphasis on environmental and behavioral economics. Thesis: Local leadership, punishment and discrimination: Experimental evidence from rural Namibia

10/2008 - 06/2012 Bachelor of Science in Economics (Volkswirtschaftslehre)

Freie Universitt Berlin, Germany

Supervisor: Univ.-Prof. Dr. Ulrich Rendtel

Thematic emphasis on quantitative methods. Thesis: Schtzung der Laeken-Beschftigungsindikatoren. Ein Vergleich zwischen EU-SILC und dem amtlichen Mikrozensus (2005-2008)

WORK IN PROGRESS

DISSERTATION

- People want to stay and adapt in place A behavioral framework to study climate change adaptations (with Matthias Mayer and Björn Vollan)
- Influence of sea level rise on discounting, resource use and migration in small-island communities: An agent-based modelling approach. (with Henry, A., Egelund-Christensen, A., Hofmann, R., Vollan, B.), published in Environmental Conservation.
- Do pro-social behaviors break-down with the prospect of displacement by rising sea-levels? (with Björn Vollan)
- Solomon Islanders do not trust more in repeated interactions Experimental evidence from a binary trust game

WORKING PAPERS

- De-facto democratization: Comparing democratic and traditional leaders in rural Namibia (with Björn Vollan, Esther Blanco, Fabian Petutschnig, Sebastian Prediger)
- When female leaders believe that men make better leaders: Empowerment in communitybased water management in rural Namibia (with Rebecca Hofmann, Meed Mbidzo, Björn Vollan)
- What Determines public acceptance of migrants? Evidence from a survey-experiment on self-inflicted vs. forced migration (with Björn Vollan, Karla Henning)

PUBLICATIONS

Henry, A., Egelund-Christensen, A., Hofmann, R., Steimanis, I., Vollan, B., 2017. Influence of sea level rise on discounting, resource use and migration in small-island communities: An agent-based modelling approach. Environmental Conservation 44: 381-388 doi.org/10.1017/S0376892917000339

PRESENTATIONS

2019 6th Workshop on the Ostrom Workshop at Indiana University, Bloomington

2018 Third Annual Workshop on Experimental and Behavioral Economics

for the Environment, Hamburg; Summer School on Climate Change at PSE, Paris; ESA World Meeting, Berlin; WWF workshop 'Challenge the

Change: Key Chances for Conservation', Berlin

2016 First Annual Workshop on Experimental and Behavioral Economics for

the Environment, Osnabrück; European Meeting of the Economic Science Association, Bergen;International Conference on 'Migration and Envi-

ronmental Change', Berlin

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

• Experimental Economics (Master-level Seminar) *Philipps-Universität Marburg, Winter Term* 2016/17

- Political Economy: The effects of democratization (Master-level Seminar) Philipps-Universität Marburg, Summer Term 2018
- Supervision of multiple master's and bachelor's theses

WORK EXPERIENCE

01/2016 - present Research Fellow at the research group of Sustainable Use of Natural

Resources

Philipps-University Marburg, Germany

Junior researcher within the Robert Bosch foundation funded research project 'The shadow of the past and future: How climate change affects human behaviour'. Planning, implementing and analysing quantitative

household surveys and lab-in-the-field experiments.

7/2015 - 08/2015 Internship at the project 'Sindh Union Council and Community Economic

Strengthening Support' (SUCCESS), designing baseline survey, scoping

focus-group discussions in the project region National Rural Support Programme(NRSP), Pakistan

SKILLS

Computer MS Office, Stata, QGIS, Open Data Kit (Kobo)

Languages German (native), English (fluent)

Field Research Extended field research in Namibia, Pakistan and Solomon Islands inclu-

ding training and supervision of local research teams.